.
Good afternoon and welcome to
the FEBRUARY 11th, 2025 regular
meeting of the san francisco
board of supervisors.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll?
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chen chan present
supervisor chen chen present
supervisor dorsey dorsey
present supervisor in cardio
and cardio present supervisor
fielder fielder present
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud
present supervisor mandolin
PRESIDENT Mandell amin
PRESIDENT Supervisor melgar
present melgar present
supervisor sartor sartor
present supervisor cheryl
sherald present and supervisor
walton walton present.
>> MR. PRESIDENT all members
are present.
Thank you MADAM Clerk.
Will you please call the roll?
Oh, you just did actually.
Okay, let's try that again and
adapting the san francisco
board of supervisors
acknowledges that we are on the
unceded ancestral homeland of
the ramakrishna aloni who are
the original inhabitants of the
san francisco peninsula.
As the indigenous stewards of
this land and in accordance
with their traditions the raw
material oni have never been
have never ceded lost or
forgotten their
responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory.
as guests we recognize that we
benefit from living and working
on their traditional homelands
.
We wish to pay our respects by
acknowledging the ancestors,
elders and relatives of the
ramakrishna owning community
and by affirming their
sovereign rights as first
peoples.
>> colleagues, will you join me
in saying the pledge of
allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag
of the united states of america
and to the republic for which
stands one nation under GOD
indivisible with liberty and
justice for all.
>> on behalf of the board I
want to acknowledge the staff
at S.F. Gov tv and especially
today kaleena mendoza who
record each of our meetings and
make the transcripts available
to the public online.
And with that, MADAM Clerk can
we go to our 2 P.M. Special
order?
>> yes.
The special order at 2 P.M. Is
the appearance at today's
meeting by the honorable mayor
daniel murray PRESIDENT To
engage in a formal policy
discussion with eligible board
members prior to the discussion
the mayor MAY address the board
for up to five minutes.
>> welcome, MR. Mayor.
>> do you have any opening
remarks?
I do.
Thank you.
Thank you for having me.
Good afternoon PRESIDENT
Management and members of the
board of supervisors.
It's an honor to be here on
what is an important fun and
exciting week for our city.
I look forward to marching with
you all and the lunar new year
parade welcoming fans to san
francisco for the nba all star
weekend to ensure residents and
visitors feel safe and welcome.
Public safety is key.
Last week supervisor dorsey and
souder joined me to announce
the san francisco police
department hospitality zone
task force which will main
which will make downtown safe
and kickstart our economy.
The hospitality zone task force
will be an important part of
our public safety plan for this
weekend nba all-star game and
then lunar new year parade.
But it will continue after
those events are done.
The hospitality zone task force
will provide residents and
visitors with the security they
deserve.
365 days a year.
This new effort is part of our
diversified strategy to get san
franciscans back to work, clean
up our streets and welcome more
people to our city.
San francisco is open for
business conferences, tourism
and the community events that
make our city special.
And with your help in this new
era of collaboration, our
potential as a city is sky
high.
So thank you all for your
support on that.
>> thank you, mayor lurie.
>> MADAM Clerk, could you
please call the topic?
Yes.
The following topic is short
term operational funding for
the san francisco municipal
transportation agency offered
by supervisor melgar.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> supervisor melgar.
Thank you PRESIDENT Randleman
and good afternoon, mayor.
>> thank you for being here.
San francisco is a major global
hub of commerce, hospitality
technology, finance, education.
>> in order for all of these
sectors to thrive the way we
all want them to and for our
neighbors right here in san
francisco to be connected to
one another and to all those
sectors we rely on are public
transportation systems.
The bay area is home to many
different systems muni bart
caltrain that are
interconnected and the trains,
busses, ferries are the
backbone of our city and keep
the economy going even through
times of economic difficulty.
Nearly one third of san
franciscans do not own a car
and rely on public
transportation to get to work
to school and to complete daily
errands.
A couple of years ago we made
muni free for kids and that
affected at truancy rates and
allowed them the freedom to get
around.
>> for residents who do not own
a car.
Public transportation reduces
citywide congestion allowing
for quicker trips for everyone
.
>> a safe, accessible,
affordable public
transportation system is
essential.
An essential element of san
francisco's past and our
present in our future and a key
ingredient for the success of
our economy education system,
public health infrastructure
and the growth of the west side
which I represent part of.
Unfortunately as you know muni
is facing a current short term
budget deficit in more than
$300 million annual structural
deficit going forward.
>> we are already seeing the
impact of this possible
shortfall in you know, maybe
impending cuts this summer
without both short term and
long term fixes.
We are all but guaranteeing the
failure of some of these
elements for our city and
robbing an entire generation of
opportunities in the future.
So therefore mario, my question
is this.
Will you do everything in your
power to ensure that we can
weather the next couple of
years with no service cuts to
muni while we work together on
long term solutions for the
system?
>> thank you for the question
supervisor melgar.
I'm here to do everything in my
power to support muni's
immediate and long term health.
As you set it correctly muni is
the backbone.
It is the lifeblood of this
city.
Weekday ridership is up to
500,000 daily boardings.
Muni isn't just critical for
san francisco it's vital to the
entire region.
Over 60% of all regional
transit trips start or end in
san francisco.
Residents and visitors rely on
muni every day.
And as ridership steadily
returns to pre-pandemic levels,
it plays a vital role in our
city's economic recovery.
San francisco's chief economist
ted egan said it best if we
don't have a solvent transit
agency we will never have an
economic recovery.
No one especially myself, no
one wants to see muni service
cuts.
>> but the city's budget crisis
is real and the reality is this
is what muni MAY need to do to
solve the wider budget crisis
they're facing.
I know S.F. Mta is not only
evaluating service reductions
but they are also evaluating
all of their expenditures to
determine what can be cut back
or improved through
efficiencies.
>> so I want to work with you
supervisor melgar and all of
you the entire board of
supervisors to find long term
solutions to make muni and the
city thrive.
>> thank you, mayor lurie.
Supervisor melgar.
You MAY now ask a follow up
question directly related to
the opening question.
>> thank you, PRESIDENT.
My follow up question is what
ideas do you have for funding
sources or sources of income
for the system?
>> I was up in sacramento just
yesterday advocating for state
funding and I'm doing
everything in my power to
secure those resources.
But we need a multi-pronged
approach.
Is almost certain that we will
need both local and regional
revenue measures on the 2026
ballot to support muni's budget
and we're going to need help
with stopgap funding this year
so I can continue alongside all
of you to advocate for our
state officials for help from
sacramento.
>> thank you, mayor.
>> thank you, mayor lurie.
You MAY now ask a question to
supervisor melgar or to any
other supervisor in attendance
pertaining to the same topic
but not necessarily related to
the previous question.
I just I want to say thank you
for inviting me over.
Supervisor thank you for the
questions and look forward to
working with you all on on this
important and vital topic.
>> thank you marilyn you very
much.
>> this concludes the district
seven topic discussion.
>> thanks.
Good to see.
>> and with that this matter
has been discussed and is now
filed and then rifling back in
my papers.
MADAM Clerk let are there any
communications?
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
The san francisco board of
supervisors welcomes your
attendance in this meeting in
person in the board's
legislative chamber room 250
here on the second floor in
city hall.
You MAY watch the proceeding on
S.F. Govee tv's channel two x
or view the live stream at w w
w dot S.F. Geo vtv.Org.
>> you can submit your public
comment in writing by either
sending an email to bos at S.F.
Gov.Org or the U.S. Postal
service to the san francisco
board of supervisors.
>> the number one DR. Carlton b
goodlatte place city hall room
244 san francisco, california
941022 make a reasonable
accommodation request under the
americans with disabilities act
or to request language
assistance please contact the
clerk's office at least two
business days in advance by
calling (415) 554-5184.
Thank you members.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
And I believe that takes us to
the approval of meeting
minutes.
Today we are approving the
meeting minutes from the
JANUARY 8th, 2025 inaugural
board meeting.
Does anyone have any changes to
these meeting minutes?
Seeing none.
Can I have a motion to approve
the minutes as presented moved
by dorsey seconded by melgar.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on the minutes as
presented?
Supervisor fielder fielder eyes
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I.
Supervisor randleman hi
randleman I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sartor
sartor I supervisor cheryl
cheryl I supervisor walton
walton I supervisor chen chen I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
either are lebanese.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk.
Without objection the minutes
will be approved after public
comment as presented.
Let's go to the consent agenda
items one through nine items
two through five, MR.
PRESIDENT.
>> absolutely.
Items two through five.
>> yes.
These items so much these items
are on consent.
They MAY be considered routine
if a member objects an item MAY
be removed and considered
separately.
All rights I don't see well
does anyone want to remove
anything from the consent
agenda?
I don't see anything without
objection these well MADAM
Clerk can we take that same
house and call if you could,
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> okay then let's take that
same house, same call.
Without objection, these
ordinance ordinances are
finally passed.
>> and with that, MADAM Clerk,
let's go to the regular agenda
unfinished business item six
item six this item amends the
business and tax regulations
code pertaining to commercial
vacancy tax exemption pursuant
to article 29 section 20 909 of
the business and tax
regulations code.
Final passage of this ordinance
today requires an affirmative
vote of two thirds of the
entire membership of the board.
That's eight votes.
>> all right.
And I think we can take this
same house, same call without
objection.
The ordinance is finally passed
.
>> MADAM Clerk, please call
item seven.
Item seven this is an ordinance
to amend the administrative
code to provide that to provide
for the core initiatives to
strengthen the city's response
to homelessness, drug abuse,
mental health needs and related
crises.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on item seven
supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor of mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor randleman all right,
gentlemen I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton no
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I then
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are ten eyes and one no
with supervisor walton voting
no thank you MADAM Clerk can
you please call item eight a oh
nope.
>> the ordinance is finally
passed.
>> MADAM Clerk can you please
call inmate yes.
Item eight this is an ordinance
to appropriate 526,000 from the
general reserve to the san
francisco municipal
transportation agency to
support free two hour parking
in the portsmouth square
parking garage JANUARY 28th
through FEBRUARY 28th, 2025 and
transit fares for the lunar new
year parade weekend on FEBRUARY
15th and 16th 2025 for the
fiscal year 2024 through 2025.
>> and can you please call the
roll on item eight supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmoud mahmoud I supervisor
randleman I randleman I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chan I
supervisor chin chin i
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio in cardio
either are elevenses without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk can you please call item
nine item nine this is a
resolution to authorize the
human services agency to apply
for and accept the county
allocation award under the
california department of
housing and communities
development transitional
housing program for
approximately 4.2 million and
the housing navigation and
maintenance program for 630,000
to provide funding to assist
young adults to secure and
maintain housing.
And I think we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
MADAM Clerk, will you please
call item ten?
>> item ten.
Approves a retro active grant
agreement with the young
community developers for the
following programs black to the
future and the school site
mentoring program for a five
year term JULY 1st 2024 through
JUNE 30th 2029 and for
approximately 12.4 million.
Supervisor walton thank you
PRESIDENT MADAM and colleagues.
Item ten is a grant to young
community developers my former
employer.
I do not have a financial
relationship with y c d nor
have I since I left over six
years ago and I do not have a
conflict of interest on this
item but to avoid the
appearance of any conflict I
would like to ask for a motion
to excuse me from participating
in this retroactive item.
>> all right.
Is there a motion to excuse
zero so walton made by fielder
seconded by melgar.
>> I think we can take that
without objection and then
MADAM Clerk, can you call the
roll on the item on item ten
supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor mandel bin hi
randleman I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are ten I's thank you
MADAM Clerk without objection
this resolution is adopted.
Can you please call our next
item item 11 this is a
resolution to approve the first
amendment to an agreement with
bay area community resources
for following programs sunset
media waive reset just as
collaborative the youth line
technology pathway and career
pathways for undocumented youth
to increase the contract amount
by 1.5 million for a new total
of 10.4 million with no change
to the five year term through
JUNE 30th 2029.
>> please call the roll in this
item I'm item 11 supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
mahmoud mahmoud I supervisor
randleman hi mendelson I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chen chen I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are 11 eyes without
objection the resolutions
adopted MADAM Clerk can you
please call item 12 item 12
resolution to approve and
authorize the general manager
of the san francisco public
utilities commission to execute
a contract water capital
program management with hdr
stantec jv to provide program
management consulting services
to support delivery of the
water enterprise and hedge
hagee water capital improvement
program and the water system
improvement program for 80
million and with the duration
of ten years with an
anticipated timeframe from
APRIL 2025 through MARCH 2035
and I think we can take this
same house same call without
objection the resolutions
adopted MADAM Clerk, can you
please call item 12 or item 13
rather item 13 is a resolution
to approve a third amendment
with a lease lease use and
operating agreement for a bart
station and related facilities
and grant of easement at san
francisco international for a
rent credit in support of the
san francisco bay area rapid
transit transit district's next
generation fare gates
replacement project for 3.15
million with no changes to the
term of of JUNE 20th 2nd to
2000 and three through JUNE
21st 2053.
>> we will take this item same
house, same call without
objection the resolution is
adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 14 item 14 resolution
to approve the fourth amendment
to the grant agreement between
the city acting by and through
the department of homelessness
in support of housing and
catholic charities for the S.F.
Home rapid rehousing program
for families to extend the
grant term by 16 months
FEBRUARY 28th 2025 for a new
term of JULY first 2018 through
JUNE 30th 2026 to increase the
amount by approximately 4.7
million and a new total of 14.5
million and we can take this
item same house, same call
without objection the
resolution is adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item 15 item 15 this is an
ordinance to approve the
amended airport surveillance
technology a new policy
governing the use of automated
license plate readers ground
transportation management
system and parking assist
parking guidance system.
>> we can take this item same
house, same call without
objection the ordinance is
passed on first reading MADAM
Clerk can you please call item
number 16 item 16 this is a
motion to appoint supervisor
belal mahmoud to the bay area
air quality management district
board of directors term ending
FEBRUARY first, 2029 or the
conclusion of his term as a
member of the board of
supervisors.
>> is there a motion to excused
supervisor mahmud I moved by
melgar seconded by cheryl.
We can take that without
objection.
>> supervisor mahmud is excused
if and on the motion MADAM
Clerk, will you please call the
roll on item 16 supervisor
fielder fielder I supervisor
randleman hi mendelson I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor sartor sutter I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are ten eyes without
objection the motion is
approved MADAM Clerk can you
please call item 17 and 18
together?
>> item 17 and 18 are two
motions to appoint supervisor
connie chan to the san
francisco bay conservation and
development commission and free
city college oversight
committee for an indefinite
term or the conclusion of her
term as a member of the board
of supervisors.
Colleagues can I have a motion
to excuse supervisor chan moved
by mahmud seconded by chen.
We can take that without
objection supervisor chan is
excused.
And then on the motions.
>> MADAM Clerk, will you please
call the roll and item 17 and
18 supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor mandelson hi
middleman I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervise her sadr
sadr I supervisor cheryl cheryl
I supervisor walton I walton I
soup her chin chin I supervisor
dorsey dorsey I and supervisor
in cardio and cardio I their
attorneys without objection
these motions are approved
MADAM Clerk will you please
call item 19 item 19 this is a
motion to appoint supervisor
danny sadr to the golden gate
bridge highway and
transportation district board
of directors term ending
JANUARY 31st 2027 or the
conclusion of his term as a
member of the board of
supervisors.
>> colleagues can I have a
motion to excuse supervisor
sadr from voting on this matter
moved by chen second by walton
without objection the
supervisor sadr is excused.
>> and on the motion MADAM
Clerk, will you please call the
roll on item 19 supervisor
fielder fielder I.E. Supervisor
mahmoud mahmoud I supervisor
randleman hi mendelson I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton I walton I
supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are ten eyes without
objection the motion is
approved MADAM Clerk could you
please call items 20 through 22
together items 20 through 22
are three motions that appoint
supervisor matt dorsey to the
outside boards or commissions
for the four an alternate
member to the san francisco bay
conservation and development
commission for an indefinite
term item 21 to the reentry
council term ending JUNE 1st
2026 or the conclusion of his
term as member of the board and
for adam, 22, as a member to
the association of bay area
executive board term ending
JUNE 30th 2025 or the
conclusion of his term as a
member of the board.
>> colleagues can I have a
motion to excuse supervisor
dorsey from voting on these
matters moved by cheryl
seconded by mahmoud without
objection supervisor dorsey is
excused.
>> and on the motions MADAM
Clerk, will you please call the
roll on items 20 through 22
supervisor fielder fielder eyes
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor randleman hi
management I supervisor melgar
I melgar I supervisor sadr sadr
I supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton walton I
supervisor chan chin eyes
supervisor chin chin I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are ten eyes without
without objection the motions
are approved MADAM Clerk can
you please call item 23 item 23
a motion to appoint supervisor
myrna melgar to the
metropolitan transportation
commission term ending FEBRUARY
10th 2027 or the conclusion of
her term as a member of the
board of supervisors colleagues
can I have a motion to excuse
supervisor melgar from voting
on this matter moved by field
or seconded by sauder and we
can take that without objection
supervisor melgar is excused
and on the motion MADAM Clerk
can you please call the roll?
>> oh, and item 23 supervisor
fielder fielder I.E. Supervisor
mahmud ahmad I supervisor
randleman all right gentlemen I
supervisor sadr sadr I
supervisor cheryl cheryl I
supervisor walton hi walton I
supervisor chin chin am
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are ten I's thank you
MADAM Clerk without objection
the motion is approved
congratulations and thank you
colleagues for stepping up to
serve on these various boards.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call item number two for item
20 four was referred without
recommendation from the rules
committee.
It's a resolution to accept the
san francisco sheriff's office
military equipment use policy
2024 annual report and
inventory and to approve the
request for purchase and use of
the additional equipment
consistent with the criteria
set forth in state law.
>> supervisor chen thank you
PRESIDENT.
>> I would like to make a
motion referring item 24 back
to the rules committee for
amendments and I have been
working with this year with our
sheriff miyamoto to introduce
some amendments regarding the
acquisition of our pepper ball
launchers.
>> the amendments will refer to
the usage guidelines in the pop
up menus and this manufacturer
guidelines in the product menu
for the pepper ball we spro
launchers and munitions include
four of the amendments one it's
never a point or discharge the
launcher at any time that and
anything that we do not intend
to suit.
>> the second one is increasing
the velocity of this product
increase the risk of death and
injury and the third bullet
point is never discharge our
launcher at the personal
property of others.
And last one is keep all pepper
ball put projectiles and
launchers out of the site and
rich off children's.
All right.
Thank you.
Supervisor chen supervisor
walton one I'd like to second
the motion to send back to
committee but just also want to
state for the record that we
have already had some negative
impacts with chemical weapons
from the sheriff's department.
>> we've actually had children
in san mateo county school that
is located next to the jail in
the environment have also
already received chemical
impacts from testing and
training at the san bruno
county jail site.
There continues to be an
ongoing investigation of the
harms of these chemical weapons
used by the department and so
this is always been a red flag
for me so I appreciate
supervisor chin sending this
back to committee but I hope
that we get the results of the
investigation very soon or even
when we come back to the full
board.
There's no way I would support
those chemical weapons.
>> supervisor fielder thank
you, PRESIDENT.
I want to thank my colleague
supervisor chen for working on
the amendments.
I also have concerns for all
the reasons that supervisor
walton noted and and also the
just the the limited role of of
sheriffs in our city security
at jails, hospitals, city
buildings.
>> I definitely have major
concerns about how these will
be deployed and and what other
equipment exists in the
department's inventories and
why at this time especially in
our budget deficit are these
being considered?
>> so thank you.
Thank you.
Supervisor fielder is there a
representative of the sheriff's
office here?
>> come on up.
>> good afternoon.
Board chief john ramirez with
the sheriff's office, the
sheriff's office have any
objection to our rules having
another look at this?
>> no, we don't.
>> all right.
Thank you.
Then the motion has been made
and seconded to send this to
rules and I guess and on that,
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on the motion to
send item 24 to the rules
committee?
Supervisor fielder fielder I
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor randleman hi
randleman I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sutter
sutter I supervisor cheryl
cheryl eyes supervisor walton
high walton eyes supervisor
chin chin eyes supervisor chin
chin eyes supervisor dorsey
dorsey eye and supervisor and
cardio and gaudio I there are
11 eyes thank you.
>> thank you MADAM Clerk and I
would just as a mild admonition
ask colleagues to the extent
that they can to get their
amendments into committee well
while the mat matters are still
pending before committee it
can't always happen.
Sometimes things do get sent
back to committee but as a best
practice that's ideal.
MADAM Clerk, can you please
take us to our 30 2:30 P.M.
Special order?
>> yes.
This is the recognition of
commendations for meritorious
service to the city and county
of san francisco and I think we
have one commendation today and
that is from supervisor walton
in district ten.
>> thank you so much, PRESIDENT
MADAM in the legacy of black
excellence is built upon the
dedication and resilience and
unwavering commitment of
individual girls like officer
jason johnson, jason, if you
could come on up.
Officer jason johnson better
known as officer jj is a 17
year veteran of the san
francisco police department.
He has not only upheld his duty
to serve and protect but has
gone beyond the badge to uplift
and empower the next generation
through his visionary
leadership officer jj founded
operation genesis inc., a
transformative program that
bridges coaches and builds
identity by taking youth and
adult chaperons on life
changing journeys to ghana
africa.
His work extends far beyond
this initiative he has
spearheaded programs like
genesis academy a journey to
self-discovery youth career
academy blow up girls group
body engineer fitness community
essential relief and
neighborhoods united each of
these programs reflects his
deep commitment to mentoring
guiding and supporting over 300
youth and their families
particularly in the bayview.
Officer jay's impact is
immeasurable.
He is a mentor, a role model
and a beacon of hope for
countless young people thriving
to see beyond their
circumstance choices and reach
their full potential.
His dedication to fostering
self-discovery, career
development and community
engagement is a testament to
his belief in the power of
transformation and collective
progress as we celebrate black
history month we recognize
offer jay's officer jj as a
modern day changemaker someone
who is not only shaping the
present but laying the
foundation for a future where
every young person has the
opportunity to rise.
His work embodies the true
spirit of service, leadership
and black excellence.
Officer J.J., we commend you.
We honor you and we thank you.
Your impact will be felt for
generations to come.
>> thank you.
>> so I guess this is the part
where I give a speech I know
this is this is you guys yeah,
yeah, this is this is this is
pretty cool.
This is a huge honor.
You know, since I became a
police officer and you know, I
just fell in love with san
francisco.
I'm not originally from here
but I feel like I am now and
just being fully immersed into
the community.
Yeah, it's just this is great,
you know, we've served over
hundreds of community members.
We've taken over 90 people have
gone to africa and brought back
some of that culture that they
have their back to san
francisco and immersed it with
the culture we have here and
it's been tremendous and the
results you kind of see the
numbers for the how the crime
is down a part of it is what
we've done in the community,
what community members and
community members buying into
the community and giving back.
It's just been it's been
amazing.
This is such an honor and I'm
grateful.
>> thank you.
>> and I do see we have deputy
chief lazaro on here and I
don't know if you want to say
anything.
>> well, first I want to say
congratulations officer officer
J.J. And I want to thank you,
supervisor walton for making
this announcement for his
award.
And you know, oftentimes the
san francisco police
department's asked about well,
what are you doing about
community policing and what is
it to you?
And I look at officer J.J. As
one of many great examples
about how it's not just
enforcing the law, it's not
just arresting individuals but
it's what is our intervention
strategy to get people out of a
certain lifestyle of criminal
if they're involved in crime
and get them connected with
jobs and training and education
and doing all those things.
And he has been a role model
and a mentor to so many people
for so many years that this is
very fitting.
So on behalf of chief scott and
the entire san francisco police
department, I want to thank you
supervisor walton and this
entire board and I want to
congratulate J.J. For
everything you do and will
continue to do for our city to
make our city safe.
>> so thank you
so.
MADAM Clerk, let's go to
committee reports.
Please call item number 25.
>> item 25 will be considered
by the audit and oversight
committee at a regular meeting
on thursday, FEBRUARY six, 2025
and was recommended as amended
bearing the same title as a
committee report.
>> it's a resolution to
authorize the office of the
mayor, the office of the city
attorney and the office of the
city administrator and the head
of each division, office and
department under the
supervision of the city
administrator to solicit
donations from various private,
nonprofit, philanthropic and
other entities to support
services fundraising for
services related to
immigration, lgbtq plus rights
,environmental protection,
reproductive rights and racial
equity for the be hosted
payment waiver.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on this item on
item 25.
Supervisor fielder fielder is
supervisor from would mahmoud I
supervisor mandel mendelson I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor carter sutter I
supervisor cheryl cheryl eyes
supervisor walton walton absent
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor and cardio and
guardian I there are ten I's
thank you MADAM Clerk without
objection this resolution is
adopted.
Can you please call item 26?
Item 26 was considered by the
land use and transportation
committee at a regular meeting
and was forwarded as a
committee report.
It's an ordinance to amend the
planning code and the health
code for the inclusionary
housing ordinance non
non-potable water exemption we
can take this item same house,
same call without objection
this ordinance is passed on
first reading MADAM Clerk can
you please call item 27 item 27
what's considered by the rules
committee at a regular meeting
on monday FEBRUARY 10th and was
also forwarded as a committee
report.
Item 27 is a motion to appoint
supervisor jackie fielder to
the local agency formation
commission term ending FEBRUARY
4th, 2027 at the conclusion of
her term as a member of the
board.
>> colleagues can I have a
motion to excuse supervisor
fielder from voting on this
matter moved by chen seconded
by chan.
We can take that without
objection.
Supervisor fielder is excused.
>> and on the motion.
>> MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on item 27
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor randleman.
>> all right, gentlemen, I
supervisor melgar I melgar I
supervisor sartor sadr i
supervisor cheryl cheryl eyes
supervisor walton walton absent
supervisor chan chin eyes
supervisor chin chin eyes
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor in cardio and cardio
I there are nine eyes without
objection the motion is
approved MADAM Clerk let's go
to roll call for introductions
of first member up to introduce
new business is supervisor
fielder hey hello thank you
colleagues I am sure many of
you are aware of an incident
that took place in my district
on sunday night as super bowl
sunday was getting underway I
got a call from fire chief
chrisman at 350 that a car had
crashed into a parklet injuring
six including a mom and a child
who were sent as of general
under a red code for that
reason I was completely
prepared to arrive at a tragic
scene and now we know that
thankfully all six are expected
to be okay.
We know that the crash was a
result of a police chase of a
wanted vehicle that started at
stone's town and continued all
the way to 24th street in
mission district.
The horrifying crash destroyed
a parklet at a popular sports
bar that was full of people
enjoying the first quarter of
the super bowl.
>> I saw the video of the crash
myself and it is an absolute
miracle no one was killed.
>> I talked to witnesses up and
down 24th street and learned
that before the wanted car
crash into the parklet it sped
northbound on mission, crashed
into a light pole at 24th in
mission and crashed into
another parked car outside of
the mcdonald's which I noticed
on the scene had all its
airbags deployed due to the
impact.
>> I am so relieved no one was
killed but this day could have
been an even more tragic one
for our city as well the
injured victims and witnesses
while not in critical condition
and will be traumatized for a
long time.
It is unclear to me at this
time whether there was an
imminent threat to anyone's
lives before as apd began to
pursue this vehicle.
>> and as you all know, voters
passed prop eight last year
which among other things
expanded the criteria criteria
for four vehicle pursuits to
allow as of greater discretion
in those decisions between 2018
and 2023 before this new policy
was implemented as live pd
reported, 150 police chases.
38% of these ended in a
collision in JUNE 2023 a police
chase killed someone.
San francisco's new vehicle
pursuit policy loosens
restrictions on vehicle chases
beyond that of most other major
american cities.
>> and so I am submitting a
letter of inquiry to as of pd
chief scott to better
understand the circumstances
and decision making surrounding
the case.
I would like to understand one
what were the circumstances
surrounding this case and what
was the top speed of the police
car or cars involved to what is
the existing as of pd policy
regarding police chases and how
have officers been trained on
it?
Three how did this incident
comply with current as a pd
policy and how did it arrives
to the level of vehicle pursuit
that ultimately put many lives
in danger or what is the pd
protocol after a car chase that
leads to injuries or
fatalities?
Five who made the judgment call
and based on what factors?
>> six were there other options
such as drones or other
measures that could have been
deployed to avoid a vehicle
pursuit that puts lives in
danger.
Seven lastly, what
accountability mechanisms are
in place for officers whose
decisions injure innocent
bystanders and extensively
damage local businesses as of
police car chase policy calls
for police to safely apprehend
a fleeing violator without
unnecessarily endangering the
public and or officers
according to state law.
>> members of law enforcement
are also supposed to balance
the offense and need for
immediate capture against the
risks to motorists, pedestrians
and officers.
Public safety requires holding
all people accountable for the
harm that they cause no matter
who causes it.
>> and I'm doing this out of
concern for the safety of our
community and I want to ensure
that the san francisco police
department is doing all that it
can to avoid such an incident
in the future while balancing
the needs of all of our public
safety.
Thank you your honor's i
submit.
>> thank you supervisor fielder
supervisor I would submit thank
you.
Supervisor mendelsohn
colleagues I'm asking that we
adjourn today's meeting in
memory of reverend robert
crummy who passed away on
JANUARY 14th at the age of 93.
>> robert was born in new york
city in 1931.
He earned an athletic
scholarship to attend new york
university where he was the
captain of the swim team and
earned his bachelor's degree in
english and philosophy in 1954.
After graduating he attended
general theological seminary
and was ordained as a priest in
1956.
In 1962 he was recruited by
james pike, the progressive
bishop of california at the
time to invigorate the
episcopal episcopal ministries
in the mission district of san
francisco.
The following year he was
invited to preach at grace
cathedral church.
His sermon argued for the equal
treatment of and lesbians by
the church.
In 1963 he was not invited
back.
He went on to co-found the
council on religion and the
homosexual.
After police raided the group's
1965 new year's eve costume
ball, crowley and other clergy
denounced the police polices
discriminatory practice
practices in a press conference
that led to all charges being
dropped at st aidan's episcopal
church in diamond heights where
he served first as victor vicar
and later as rector.
Robert performed what is
believed to have been san
francisco's first same sex
church wedding ceremony in
1968.
He performed many more when he
became rector of trinity
episcopal church on gough.
When the church hierarchy
forbade him from officiating
weddings for same sex couples,
he responded that if he could
not marry same sex couples he
would stop performing marriage
ceremonies altogether.
Eventually he got around the
prohibition by inviting in
visiting ministers to perform
the nuptials while while he
stood by robert open trinity
kitchen to ruth brinker and
project open hand when she
outgrew her home kitchen.
Feeding men dying from
malnutrition and aids they ran
project open hand from trinity
for several years until they
found their own building.
He performed more than 70
funeral services for gay men
who died from aids
complications.
A true ally of the community
robert solidarity was not
limited to any one community or
cause.
He joined DR. Martin luther
king on his MARCH to selma,
preached in support of
farmworkers and cesar chavez
and defended nudity in north
beach bars.
His very first sermon at
trinity delivered on DECEMBER
15th, 1981 called for
then-defense secretary caspar
weinberger to resign his
membership in the episcopal
church because of his hawkish
views which ran contrary to the
church's antiwar positions.
Robert was arrested proudly,
many times for many causes.
>> in later life he was an avid
blogger and kept writing until
the end of 2024.
In one of his final blog post
titled how to stay cheerful,
robert wrote the only way I
know how to be cheerful is to
be thankful.
Positive thinking does not
work.
It avoids acknowledging pain
and sorrow.
Being thankful makes pain and
sorrow part of thankfulness.
Rest in peace and power robert
crummy.
MAY your memory be a blessing.
>> the rest I submit.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> supervisor melgar.
I thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, as I mentioned to
the mayor earlier, our public
transportation system is in a
financial crisis.
I am hopeful that all of us on
the board can commit to working
together to fill the funding
gap for muni and ensure that
the city keeps running.
Today I am introducing a
resolution affirming san
francisco's commitment to
developing fiscal solutions to
ensure that public
transportation remains safe,
affordable and convenient as an
option.
>> thank you to supervisor
sauder tenant and cardio for
your early co-sponsorship.
And MADAM Clerk I have two in
memoriam.
The first is for charles
kopecky marion.
>> we honor charles miscarrying
today.
He recently passed away at the
age of 91.
He is survived by his loving
wife of 34 years, diane, his
brother and sister, his sons,
grandchildren, nieces, nephews
and relatives who brought him
immeasurable joy.
Charles led a model life of
service and entrepreneurship.
He served our country in the
air force and was very active
in the reserves and later in
the veterans community.
>> he spent an incredible
amount of time helping boys and
girls through the boys and
girls club of santa ana and was
dedicated to his armenian
community in northern
california.
He was an active member in the
effort to save the mt. Davidson
cross in district seven and
served four years in the
council of armenian american
organizations of northern
california.
His legacy of service and
compassion will continue to
inspire and resonate for
resonate for generations to
come.
>> lastly colleagues I am
offering an in memoriam for san
francisco firefighter and san
francisco police officer bob
geary who died JANUARY 26th at
the age of 85.
Robert geary was born NOVEMBER
22nd, 1939 in oakland and he
was five minutes younger than
his twin sister patricia.
He attended zero school in
bishop o'dowd school in
oakland.
He was a seven time elected
member of the democratic
central committee and served
two terms as a on the board of
directors of the air.
>> he was one of those
characters that made san
francisco space ideal.
He was assigned to a community
policing position in north
beach and how he made it his
own was to order an expensive
wooden dummy out of a vintage
tril equis catalog.
He taught himself how to use it
in front of the mirror and he
chose the name smarty as a pun
of the word dummy and the full
name.
Brendan was smarty to add
dignity to the doll geary took
the dummy to entertain children
while he was out on patrol
dressing it in police uniform
with a badge one half and a
water pistol.
Despite carrying the dummy,
geary was able to function as
an officer chasing and tackling
at least one suspect with the
dummy at hand.
>> in 19 93 he placed a ballot
measure to the voters after
being told by his captain and
then chief ribera that he could
no longer be a ventriloquist
with a psychic proposition.
Bebe was supported by 68,000
san franciscans.
This was the second ballot
victory.
He had already won big by
championing proposition b which
saved a mounted unit from
elimination in 1988.
>> bob geary walked a beat in
north beach and retired on the
west side.
>> he will be missed by all who
knew him and voted for him.
He is survived by his twin
sister patricia and geary and
his partner in ventriloquism
brenda no marti.
The rest I submit and I would
like to be referred after
supervisor dorsey please.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
Supervisor melgar.
Supervisor sutter.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
First I'd like to build on
supervisor mcguire's words
related to bob geary.
Even many years later he is
someone who the community of
north beach remembers fondly
and share stories of.
And I think he also represented
the best of community policing
and what we subscribe to in
central station and in the
north beach community of making
our police officers and our
public safety responders part
of our neighborhoods.
>> next I'd like to introduce a
resolution recognizing the
month of FEBRUARY 2025 as
children's dental health month
in the city and county of san
francisco.
Kerri is also known as cavities
are tooth decay are the most
common chronic disease in
children across our country.
Kids only get one set of
permanent teeth and it's
crucial to protect them from
day one so they last a
lifetime.
>> when kids have poor oral
health it affects their ability
to succeed at school, to sleep,
to eat and to grow.
And we want our city to remain
committed to protecting and
improving the health of our
city's children.
Youth and families because we
know when they are healthy our
city thrives.
some of the most effective oral
habits kids can form include
brushing twice a day, flossing
every day, eating healthy food
,limiting sugary beverages and
going to the dentist for a
checkup twice a year.
I say that as much a reminder
for the children as for all of
us in this room and as an
expecting father I plan to
ensure my daughter performs all
of those healthy habits so that
no matter how big her sweet
tooth might be her teeth can
stay in good condition.
>> this resolution also
recognizes the work of cavity
free S.F. Which is a citywide
oral health collaborative
committed to addressing
children's oral health
disparities.
Our kids in chinatown, the
mission and bayview hunters
point in particular bear the
highest burden of tooth decay.
Cavity free S.F. Works to
engage with kids and parents in
those communities to support
them in accessing resources to
improve their oral health.
I want to thank nico's chinese
health coalition and their
executive director kent wu in
particular for bringing this
important issue to the
attention of our office and for
their important work in
district three to improve the
oral health of children in
chinatown.
Thank you to all ten of my
colleagues for co-sponsoring
this resolution and working to
improve the health of kids
across our city and the rest I
submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor sutter.
supervisor cheryl.
>> colleagues today I'm
introducing two items.
First, I'm introducing an
ordinance to implement a simple
amendment to the planning code
that will better allow our
corner stores to attract foot
traffic on our commercial
corridors.
We all know that our small
businesses have struggled to
recover since the pandemic.
Citywide we have persistently
low levels of tourism and
commercial vacancy rates that
remain higher than 2019 levels.
Our sales tax revenues are
lackluster compared to the
pre-pandemic years.
It is our responsibility to do
everything we can to create an
environment where small
businesses can thrive.
The legislation I am
introducing is a commonsense
code change that lets
businesses on corner lots have
to projecting signs for the two
adjoining facades further
inviting patrons and
contributing to a violent,
vibrant streetscape.
>> planning department analysis
agrees that visual cues like
signs will not only introduce
patrons to the individual
business but also draw
attention to and in court
encourage activity throughout
the entire merchant corridor.
>> amidst troubling economic
indicators and a shift away
from brick and mortar
commercial businesses, we must
do all that we can to encourage
flexible city that encourages
economic recovery.
When analyzing prior signed
legislation.
the planning department staff
also found that today nine
noncompliant businesses that
have that already have two
projecting signs are mostly
concentrated in our city's
cultural heritage districts.
We must acknowledge the
historical context of san
francisco's design controls and
the impact of past regulations
on diverse cultural expression.
Since the mid 1960s the city
has implemented sign controls
that sought to restrict quote
visual clutter.
This term is often employed as
a proxy to minimize the
expression of cultural identity
and diversity.
Recently, however, we have
rightly implemented design
guidelines in our cultural
districts that recognize the
importance of promoting and
protecting businesses that
advance the variety of cultures
that make san francisco so
unique by allowing additional
signage flexibility.
This ordinance will not just
bring these shops into
compliance with the law.
We will also ensure that more
corner stores can reflect the
artistic and cultural
identities of their
communities.
This legislation is
straightforward yet it serves
as another powerful step toward
economic revitalization and
toward fostering a welcoming,
vibrant streetscape across the
city.
>> I want to thank supervisor
sutter, supervisor melgar and
board PRESIDENT Mandel min for
your early co-sponsorship.
And I look forward to working
with all of you to gain your
support.
Furthermore, I'm joining mayor
lurie as a co-sponsor of a
resolution to execute a loan
agreement between the mayor's
office of housing and community
development and the tenderloin
neighborhood development
corporation.
This loan finances the
acquisition rehabilitation and
preservation of over 100
affordable homes in district
two located on ellis street
between goff and laguna.
This project the normandie
apartments converts 108
privately owned units into
permanently affordable housing.
>> this acquisition expands
much needed affordable housing
opportunities for low and
moderate income households in a
neighborhood with strong
transit access and senior
services.
Critically, rents in these
apartments will be capped at
30% of household income.
I'm thrilled that the normandie
apartments is a second site
acquisition in d2 and most
notably this site is one of the
lowest public cost per unit
acquisitions in the small cites
program history.
I'm grateful for the extensive
work that most city and tienda
have done to make this project
a reality.
It's pivotal that we continue
to create and preserve
affordable housing across the
city, ensuring that every
district remains accessible to
the diverse range of residents
that make san francisco the
vibrant city it is.
>> by fairness, by financing
this project we make a cost
effective investment to protect
needed affordable housing and
support a future in which all
communities can continue to
thrive and live in their homes
without the risk of the place
of displacement.
>> the rest I submit thank you
.
>> supervisor sheryl supervisor
walton.
Thank you, MADAM Clerk.
First I just want to be added
to the letter of inquiry read
supervisor fielder and the
questions around police chases.
I know at some point with the
law changes someone is actually
going to die because of these
police changes.
Intentional or not.
>> and so it's disheartening
today.
>> colleagues, I just want to
speak on a silent hearing that
I introduced last week.
I introduced the hearing
regarding the mistreatment of
residents at the alice griffith
apartments by mccormack berrien
salazar and property management
around the quality of services
they are providing mistreatment
of residents and oversight
responsibilities.
Our office has heard from
numerous residents about the
lack of services as well as
quality of life issues.
We are requesting the san
francisco housing authority
john stuart company, mccormack
bear and salazar office of
community investment in
infrastructure five point
bayview hunters point multi
senior services and the mayor's
office of housing and community
development to report at this
hearing.
>> there have been other
hearings that we've held around
public housing communities here
in this body and we've most
certainly had some successes as
a result of these hearings.
It's unfortunate that we have
to go through the trouble of
calling a hearing to make sure
that the quality of life for
our residents are met and their
needs are met.
But this is something that
continues to be a problem in
some of our our housing
communities.
And so we're going to continue
to fight to make sure residents
have the services and the
quality of life that they
deserve.
>> the rest I submit thank you
.
Supervisor walton.
Supervisor chen submit.
Thank you.
Supervisor dorsey.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
Colleagues, I have requested
the city attorney advice and
begun the process of preparing
a formal legislative drafting
request in response to a recent
police commission resolution
urging this body to amend
relevant provisions of the san
francisco administrative code
that govern rewards for
information pertaining to
unsolved homicide cases.
In general this would seek to
address expanding rewards for
information leading to the file
filing of homicide charges
rather than solely for criminal
convictions and potentially
certain other circumstances for
which I will need to work more
closely with our city attorney.
I would however, like to extend
my gratitude to MISS Paulette
brown for her advocacy for this
and also for her long time
support of those who like her
have suffered the loss of a
family member or loved one to
homicides that remain unsolved
for many years.
MS. Brown has been nothing
short of the conscience of the
san francisco police commission
reminding us of law
enforcement's important and
enduring work to do justice and
to offer a measure of closure
for those left behind in the
wake of tragedy.
To the extent we policymakers
can incentivize information
that MAY help law enforcement's
task in solving homicides, we
should do so.
And I look forward to working
with advocates, with colleagues
and with our city attorney's
office to accomplish that.
>> separately, I would like to
reserve the right to offer a
more complete in memoriam next
week.
But we received sad news of the
passing earlier this morning of
a true sun of san francisco a
long time labor leader, a
conscientious civil service
commissioner and an admired and
beloved leader of san
francisco's irish-american and
roman catholic communities in
ethics.
Crowley.
For those of us who knew ethics
as a friend, I think we still
have some processing and
grieving to do before we can
collaborate on an in memoriam
that is fully worthy of alex's
remarkable legacy to the city
he loved.
Preliminarily, however, I would
ask that we also adjourn
today's meeting in honor of
ethics.
Crowley extending our
condolences to his beloved
family members, his wife nancy
and his children jill, robbie,
carrie and meg.
Our hearts go out to all of you
in this difficult time and the
rest I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey supervisor
melgar, thank you so much,
MADAM Clerk.
Thank you, supervisor dorsey.
I also just wanted to weigh in
as commissioner crowley was a
friend and was a constituent up
until two years ago when that a
neighborhood with redistricted
into district four.
I wanted to highlight a little
bit commissioner crowley's
great contributions to the
labor movement in san francisco
and as a civic leader and civil
servant.
Commissioner crowley at joined
I see the stagehand at union
and if he served for 30 years
he was a member union member of
society at local 16 and he
began his career as a stagehand
in 1982 working for the san
francisco opera and broadening
his field experience in motion
pictures and performing arts.
He joined the management staff
in 1990 and was elected
PRESIDENT Of piazza local 16 in
1994.
Rising to business manager in
1997 where he was elected to
seven consecutive terms he was
a highly skilled labor
negotiate and mediator.
>> he had his own firm where he
advised folks on nonprofit
labor business negotiations.
He served as port commissioner
from 2010 to 2012 and also as
commissioner from 2008 to 2010.
He served as PRESIDENT Of that
commission from SEPTEMBER of
2009 through 2010.
Also serving on the sampras's
go labor council executive
committee and is a charter
member of the friends of the
san francisco film commission.
Commissioner crowley has served
three terms on the travis san
francisco travel board of
directors and also as a member
of the san francisco cork
ireland sister city committee.
We will MISS Him dearly.
He was also a candidate for
supervisor of district seven.
His wife nancy also a dear
friend is an avid cyclist and
activist in these circles.
We send all our love to nancy
and I hope that we can close
the meeting in his memory.
>> thank you.
Let's have that be from the
full board.
>> thank you.
Supervisor melgar.
Supervisor walton, you asked to
be re referred on this item.
>> thank you so much, MADAM
Clerk.
My apologies, colleagues.
I'm also requesting a hearing
on the budget and legislative
analyst's performance audit of
the san francisco police
department over time requested
by former supervisor dean
preston.
I want to thank him and his
staff for initiate this audit
with the bla.
The findings in this report
raise serious concerns about
accountability oversight and
financial management within
S.F. Pd and fiscal year 2022
2023 S.F. Police overtime
expenditures totaled 108.4
million.
Yet just 12% of officers were
responsible for 32% of all
overtime hours.
At the same time sick leave and
injury related leave among
sworn staff increased by 77%
over five years.
With troubling patterns
suggesting potential abuse, the
audit also found that cpd
failed to enforce absenteeism
policies did not adequately
monitor attendance and violated
key provisions of its mou with
the police officers association
resulting in 51,000 ineligible
ten b overtime hours between
2020 and 2023.
Additionally, 13 percent of
overtime cards were improperly
approved with the missing or
duplicate signatures and even
officers approving their own
overtime.
Perhaps most concerning S.F. Pd
spent over 30.8 million in
general fund dollars on 319,945
overtime hours for special
initiatives without clear
performance metrics or
oversight.
These findings demand answers.
>> I'm calling on both the
budget and legislative analysts
and as a pd to report on these
issues and explain how they
plan to correct these systemic
failures.
San franciscans deserve
transparency and accountability
in how our public safety
dollars are spent.
The rest I submit, is for real
this time.
>> thank you, supervisor walton
,supervisor and cardio
colleagues.
I'd like to express my
condolences to the family of f
crowley.
He was a neighbor.
He lived not too far from me
such a respected member of the
community when I was brand new
to politics he was a front
runner for supervisor.
I learned so much from him and
perhaps most importantly him
and nancy raised some great
kids.
So my condolences to crowley's
family.
>> the rest I submit thank you
supervisor and guardian.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, seeing no
names on the roster that
concludes the introduction of
new business.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk.
>> let's go to public comments.
At this time the board welcomes
your public comment.
Please line up on your right
hand side of the chamber along
the curtains.
You MAY speak to the mayoral
appearance today the approval
of the meeting minutes as
presented.
Other general matters not on
today's agenda but within the
board subject matter
jurisdiction.
All other agenda content has
been reported out to the board
by an appropriate committee
where the public comment
requirement occurred.
We are setting the timer for
two minutes and will welcome
our first speaker.
Welcome MS. Brown.
Good morning.
i mean I said I'm sorry.
I like to use it over here and
I want to thank you matt darcy
for speaking on the resolu
ation is over here working now
I'm here concerning my son
aubrey zappacosta who was
murdered AUGUST 14, 2006 as
matt darcy spoke about about
unsolved homicides I bring
these pitches with me because
they're all unsolved homicides
and these cases have never been
set.
So this is a new new one of all
unsolved homicides and there
are people of color are
unsolved homicides and I say
this because I'm a mother have
been fighting for years about
my son.
This is me standing over my son
lifeless body.
This is something I have to
remember for the rest of my
life.
>> so that's why I asked for
this to be done.
This is my son's corpse.
This is what I see.
So I'm saying that if we can
implement this new resolution
and max carter over stone was
the one that implemented this
at the border.
He's the the vice PRESIDENT At
the board at the police
commission.
So he MAY implement this and
I'm hoping that the board of
supervisors can help us mothers
heal.
We need we need our cases
solved.
I've been doing this for almost
20 years for my 17 year old boy
who was shot been to different
supervisors, different days,
different police chiefs,
different everybody and I have
to start all over again and
start all over again.
>> what can we do please
approve this resolution.
>> I thank dean preston for the
street renaming of the street
renaming of the 1500 block of
my son.
I see that every day and I
thank GOD for that and I thank
all of you that showed up.
But please implement this
resolution that matt dorsey
just to read to you.
>> thank you.
Thank you, MS..
Brown for your comments.
Okay.
>> welcome to the next speaker
.
>> good afternoon.
I want to make this real quick
perjury, forgery, fraud,
identity theft.
Everything was taken wrongfully
from me.
I had two pieces I'm still
getting attacked, still getting
wrongfully arrested outside the
the shelter I'm at they're
coming inside the shelter.
>> nobody's doing nothing.
But yet if I hit an officer I
go to prison, right?
>> so my lawyers come up with a
new tactic because my service
dog got kicked.
>> see, I'm going to get my I'm
going to get my justice.
The investigation's taking so
long when my lawyer is due to
the fact of all the officials
involved in fact I brought
videos to this man's office and
he ran behind the wall like a
coward.
>> yes, sir.
So this is what my lawyers are
doing investigating each single
one of you because when i
brought this to your attention,
you should have launched off an
investigation.
In fact, we got two people that
cheated on their spouse, so I'm
going to ruin your reputation
as you being behind this table
and these deaths doing your
jobs as well as your home
lives.
>> you can bank on it.
MR. Dorsey.
I do like you, sir.
Sir, remember to address your
comments to the board as a
whole.
>> I do appreciate what you do
as well as a couple other
people in here but I can assure
you ladies and gentlemen, my
lawyers are ruthless and the
investigator your team is
ruthless.
You're going to give me my
justice.
You're going to stop these
officers and my ex who's a
registered sex offender for
assaulting a child under the
age of five.
>> that's you you're helping.
You're going to get my justice
or don't I don't care.
We're going to take it and then
you're going to get humiliated
with your jobs and with your
families you can take on it.
And they tried to arrest me
again yesterday for not paying
to get on the bus.
They stopped me from being able
to get my id here in california
and stopped me from getting my
cash out of my bank.
>> ladies, gentlemen, y'all
have a beautiful day.
You know why I'm happy for you
to find out.
>> thank you for your comments.
Let's hear from our next
speaker, MR. Amen.
>> good to see you, angela
cavell, thank you for your time
today.
Thank you for the reelection of
connie chan in this south
supervisor melgar let me see I
see your district five where
I've been for 24 years at the
oasis apartments between
leavenworth and I.
I help you, sir joel you're
able to keep your position.
I read something about the
great highway.
I know some places that are
familiar and some are not.
Congrats.
Elections supervisor ralph
hillman and I want to thank you
for yourself supervisor
management and jackie thornhill
for helping sylvia margulies
who passed away on JULY 12th.
He was a retired doctor who
died of cancer, a supervisor
ralph hillman.
And then you did a lot for
sylvia as well as jackie
thornhill over and over.
I'm grateful to see all of you.
The last board was magnificent
and I know you all do a good
job.
Be safe and be well.
Thank you for your time.
>> bye bye.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker good afternoon
supervisors and all the other
people in the chamber.
My name is tina martin and I'm
a member of transit justice.
You might have guessed that
that's what I'm here to speak
about from the way I'm
decorated I think it's really,
really important that we
support our public
transportation and I really
appreciate what supervisor mel
gar said today and the
questions that she asked.
I don't feel it was
sufficiently answered and I'm
disappointed because I really
thought this was going to be a
presentation of a plan to save
public transports motion my
favorite saying I've been
taking muni since 1966 and in
many many different roles is a
mother with a toddler, an
infant babysitting going to
school and now as a retiree I
get all over the place on muni
and I really love it and I
really want to see that is
supported.
Maybe that over time problem we
have with a police department
could go the money that's being
wasted in the systemic failure
could go to public
transportation.
I don't know how these things
work but it's got to work and
my favorite saying is when done
by the mayor of bogota, former
mayor who said the progressive
city is not one where even the
poor have cars.
>> it's one where even the rich
take public transportation.
So let's see that we support
it.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
Good afternoon.
Supervisors and staff.
My name is cyrus hall.
I'm a sustainable
transportation advocate.
I'm also a district seven
resident and today I'm speaking
as part of the muni now muni
forever campaign I urge the
board to work together with
mayor o'leary to find the $15
million needed to stop the 4%
service cuts planned for this
summer.
Sfm today has spent the last
five years tightening its belt
.
The agency runs somewhere
between 80 and 90% of
pre-pandemic service.
And while muni has already cut
a number of routes, they have
also drastically increased on
time consistency service with
new transit only lanes headway
management and a muni metro
that rarely has delays public
opinion is at an all time high
yet many routes are now
bursting at the seams with
riders and our economic
headwinds present a monumental
financial challenge starting in
fiscal year 27.
>> this is a challenge we can
meet if we try.
Most immediately the board
could transfer 15 million from
the general reserve to sfm to
to alleviate the need for
summer cuts.
That's the same fund that was
used today for free parking for
a month and for free transit
for the 15th and the 16th.
>> the 4% cuts planned for this
summer would likely remove
additional routes one that I
use the 36 teresita would be
cut back to one bus every 45
minutes.
>> this is a level of service
that will ensure lower
ridership and doom the lines to
being fully removed during
future cuts that will leave my
disabled neighbors have no
choice but to use paratransit
service in the medium term the
city needs to face this crisis
heads head on and work towards
holding a special election this
year to raise the revenue.
The alternative is we would run
smack into the $320 million
deficit next year which would
imply 30% service cuts.
>> so let's all work together.
>> let's figure out how to
solve this.
Thank you so very much.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> hello supervisors.
My name is sara.
I live in d5 five and like so
many folks in the room and more
importantly hundreds and
thousands of people not in this
room I rely on muni if you as a
governing body in partnership
with the mayor are not serious
about finding funny finding
funding for muni service this
year and into the future you
are not serious about the
future of san francisco if
you're not serious about
funding muni you're not serious
about safety and muni safely
brings people to and from work
school and leisure with far
fewer fatalities and
automobiles.
If you're not serious about
funding muni you're not serious
about economic recovery.
There is no downtown recovery
or neighborhood vibrancy
without muni service.
If you're not serious about
funding muni you are not
serious about facing the
effects of climate change.
Public transportation is one of
the strongest most financially
efficient ways to fight climate
change.
the gravity of cutting muni
service won't just affect
safety, the economy and the
environment it will affect
individuals, artists, teachers,
students, nurses, engineers,
service workers and according
to our city charter and at
least once a week this very
governing body hundreds of
thousands of people ride muni
every day totaling over half a
million daily trips.
Now imagine all of those folks
in the room with us would be
more packed in the 30 at at
rush hour.
Now imagine letting each one of
them know that you couldn't
figure out funding for their
bus line or train.
Now imagine letting them know
that you could figure it out.
Sure.
>> that one feels a little bit
better, huh?
So supervisors and to wherever
you're listening, mayor lurie,
if you're not serious about
funding muni you are not
serious about serving san
francisco.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Let's hear from our next
speaker.
Welcome.
No outburst from the public,
please.
Well I'm sorry.
Hello board of supervisors.
My name is jackie liquido ba
I'm a frequent voter in
district eight and I take muni
everywhere.
I'm here to urge this board to
reject any cuts to muni service
in san francisco especially
those that would cut service
hours to 10 P.M. Or any plans
that would cut lines most taken
by residents of the tenderloin
western addition and fillmore.
I love this city and I didn't
leave the conservative state I
grew up in to come here and
watch the same forces shredding
public infrastructure and
funding federally do so here we
should be setting an example
for the nation by doing the
opposite and ensuring our
transit system is prioritized,
well funded and expanded.
>> there was a proposition on
the ballot that would have
eliminated this problem tax
rideshare companies fully
funded muni and the majority of
S.F. Voters said yes on it.
But dark money groups like grow
S.F. And together have put
their weight behind a
proposition that was written
with a poison pill to kill
proposition l even if it passed
,most voters were not aware of
this by design those shady
groups backed the campaigns of
many city officials including
some in this room.
The people of san francisco
tried to fix this problem.
It would be shameful for those
complicit in killing
proposition l to community
service now I urge you to vote
no on any cuts so that we can
have a transit system worthy of
a major city and stay in line
with our climate and equity
goals.
>> if the issue is the budget
deficit I'm sure we can shift
funding priorities around
starting with not funding
further military and chemical
weapons for sfpd as I mentioned
earlier in this meeting.
>> thank you.
thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker please.
>> good afternoon.
I am the win.
I'm a voter in district five.
I'm here this afternoon to also
urge you to prioritize funding
muni service and to prevent
harmful service cuts.
As someone who does not own a
car I rely on muni service to
go about my daily life on lines
that are in danger of being cut
.
>> muni is a primary way I'm
able to enjoy our city, move
around, visit our cities,
engage our community and
patronize our small businesses
.
>> decreased muni service means
more cars on the road which
means more traffic for
motorists higher risk of injury
to pedestrians and cyclists and
increased greenhouse gas
emissions.
Muni directly supports our
city's public safety, economy
and climate goals.
In the shadow a presidential
administration that is seeking
to dismantle infrastructure and
undo climate progress.
S.F. Should be an example of a
city that chooses to invest in
public transit.
>> the voters have made it
clear that they support funding
muni with the majority of
voters voting yes on prop eight
this past NOVEMBER.
It's crucial that the board of
supervisors work with the mayor
and ask to find solutions that
are alternatives to cutting
service.
I salute you use your
leadership and power to fund
muni's future to ensure that it
can continue to serve our city
and its people.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon, burt.
I am christopher peterson and I
live in the ingleside.
Aside from my own feet muni is
my primary mode of
transportation.
I'd like to start off by
thanking supervisor melgar for
raising the issue of muni
funding with the mayor today
and for her other comments.
I urge this board to take
action to avoid the need for
serious cuts in muni service
this summer.
The board can do this in at
least two ways.
First the board should support
sfm to in its own efforts to
raise revenue.
Unfortunately the board in the
past hasn't always done this.
In particular the board should
support expanding where and
when fees are charged for on
street parking.
This would be good both for
muni and small businesses.
It increased parking turnover
thereby increasing parking
availability for customers who
prefer to drive.
Second, the board should
establish new additional
funding for muni at least until
ballot measures are passed
establishing new long term
sources of funding for muni.
As a citizen economist ted egan
has pointed out the city's
economic recovery depends on a
healthy public transit system
shutting down muni metro at 10
P.M. For example would be
devastating for the city's
nightlife and performing arts
organizations.
Please be creative and generous
in establishing new funding for
muni.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
Hi my name is sarah greenwald
and with 350 san francisco.
>> and I was just thinking, you
know with all the challenges
the city everybody is facing
now it's easy to forget san
francisco's a fantastic city.
It's got these beautiful views.
It's got all this greenery and
the parks and and you know,
it's a center of learning and
innovation and and culture and
the arts and and a transit
system I would point out that
is fabled in song and story.
It's worked really well for a
really long time.
It's older than a lot of the
systems in the country.
And I often also mentioned that
it's tremendous benefit to the
climate.
And the mayor was just
reminding us that you think of
somebody getting on muni that
happens half a million times a
day even now after covid.
>> so I would just say let's
keep this thing running.
>> thank you for your comments
.
>> welcome.
Next speaker.
>> hi, my name is annabel
little john bailey.
I'm not with an organization
but I'm a resident of district
three in the tenderloin.
>> I rely on the 38 to get
everywhere I go.
I take it to work.
i take it to the grocery store
which is especially important
for tenderloin residents
because so many services we
need are not accessible within
our own community.
>> I just urge urge you very
very strongly to find a budget
solution before cuts are made.
The 38 is already incredibly
packed as are many of the most
popular bus lines and we
require as residents without a
car the bus and the muni to
take us where we need to go.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
Good afternoon.
Board of supervisors.
>> my name is young and I'm a
resident of cavalli district
eight.
>> I'm also a doctor.
I work at the sutter hospitals
across the city from the one up
on venice down to the one on
mission bernal.
I have a clinic at pac heights
so I take transit to work every
day.
>> so transit is a service
that's deeply important to me.
>> but more importantly, I'm
here today because many of my
patients have told me that they
either don't own a car or they
can't drive and they rely on
muni to get to their doctor's
appointments.
>> these are people who are the
most vulnerable in our city.
>> and if you make these
service cuts they will have
even harder time getting access
to health care.
>> the other thing that I want
to say is that this budget
deficit as of now should not be
and cannot be expected to solve
this problem on its own.
>> the board of supervisors and
the mayor have just as much
responsibility to find a
solution without resorting to
service cuts.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> speaker welcome.
Good afternoon supervisors.
I'm dillon fabris, community
and policy manager at san
francisco transit riders and
member of the muni know me
forever campaign.
Last week the S.F. Mta proposed
three scenarios that would
bring devastating service cuts
to every corner of our city.
Cuts could include ending muni
service hours earlier
increasing wait times up to 45
minutes shortening and even
entirely eliminating some lines
.
Every one of these cuts will
hurt riders who depend on muni
to get around the city and
access city life.
San francisco loves muni but we
also need muni expanding access
to affordable and reliable
transit as a cornerstone to
meeting so many of our city's
goals from climate to safety to
housing to downtown recovery to
economic recovery in our
neighborhoods.
Allowing muni to crumble will
make it even harder for us to
address each of these issues
and more.
For several years now the mta
has been doing what it can to
find efficiencies and prepare
for its deficit.
It was ahead of the game when
it came to implementing its
hiring freeze.
It streamlined its schedule and
cut down on operating
inefficiencies and has raised
fares and increased
enforcement.
But now we're reaching the
point where the agency's
options to balance its own
budget are limited and
unfortunately it looks like
massive cuts are coming as soon
as this summer.
But these cuts are not
inevitable.
We need the board of
supervisors to be working along
with the mayor to address this
service cuts like the emergency
that they are.
We need to be having a serious
discussion about how to fund
transit service before lines
get cut.
>> the board should be doing
all in its power to find the 15
to $50 million necessary to
prevent this year's cuts so we
can begin working toward a more
sustainable solution to address
the even larger deficits that
S.F. Mta faces next year.
This is an urgent issue for us.
It to be slowly moving towards
disaster while seemingly
nothing is happening to stop
it.
So we need the board to be
treating service cuts like they
like the problem they are for
so many san franciscans.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Welcome.
The next speaker.
>> hello.
My name is natalia.
So the cobalt I have a
privilege of living in san
francisco for the past 37 years
.
>> and during this time
unfortunately I have seen the
public transportation is
getting worse, worse and worse
.
Now I am retired.
I am living in subsidized
housing.
>> and from what I read the
busses that we use to go to the
doctor's to take to grocery
stores they are going to be
eliminated on sutter street
where I reside.
>> does several subsidized
housing for seniors like new
housing market theros for
example we are going to see the
doctors in kaiser hospital.
>> we are going to shop in
people with walkers people was
you know you seybold elderly
people it is difficult for us
really like I have never had a
car since I arrived this seat
to always use public
transportation.
>> and this is really causing a
lot of stress because 38 bus
which is very full it's you
know, overcrowded.
>> so what what is the choice
for us?
Because every year it seems
busses are going our way and we
don't have cars.
We will be balanced in the in
the houses.
We can't go anywhere.
>> we can't visit the park.
We can't enjoy the city because
we are not driving.
>> so please help us find the
money.
>> thank us.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> hi, my name is etan adler.
I'm a district three resident
and voter.
I personally take the bus
nearly every day and I make
extreme sacrifices to do so.
In one recent example I found
that the bus took about an hour
for me to to to go when it
should have taken about 20
minutes by car.
And another example it was an
hour and a half by bus for what
it was a 15 minute car ride and
I have the google maps receipts
to prove it.
I came today to give this kind
of personal stories that would
explain why muni is so
important.
But sitting here in the last
hour I changed what my
statement was going to be.
As the mayor said, we have a
real budget crisis and we have
a real and muni has a real
budget crisis that's going to
lead to service cuts.
Yet in the hour and a half that
I was sitting here more than an
hour and a half I already and
found $526,000 that we could
have used to solve the budget
in just sitting here.
I started.
>> you should continue.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> next speaker.
>> hello.
>> my name is lisa platt.
I'm a d2 resident and as a
former elected official I truly
do appreciate the budget
challenges that you're facing.
>> but we prioritize our
spending and we absolutely
cannot compromise on muni
service.
We just transferred a half
million dollars to cover free
parking for a month in transit
for two days.
So that's that's one of the
messages that we're sending and
how we're thinking about
spending our dollars.
>> we are at an absolutely
critical point.
>> we are now at the point
where it's nearly a non-viable
public transit system.
No viable system has trains
that stop running at ten.
If you aren't convinced that
it's non-viable.
Come with me as I out walk the
19 on my way to saint francis
for my auto appointments.
>> very ironic.
>> help me make that last 10
P.M. 45 bus that was cut in the
pandemic.
So I can see the final set at
the saloon and still get home
which I can't today.
>> transit is the highest roi
thing that we can do right now
.
We have a perception of crime
despite crime dropping more
people out and about on our
streets.
>> make people feel safer.
>> that's what they're looking
for is to feel a sense of
community who is going to be
there.
>> our small businesses need
the foot traffic.
>> we're talking about signage
and all of those things to get
more people into our small
businesses.
>> I could have bought one more
drink at the saloon but then it
would have cost me $25 to get
home.
>> so I beg you today to
transfer funds from the general
fund to cover the shortfall.
>> we will absolutely work with
you to find solutions to fund
muni long term.
Please avoid any service cuts.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> good afternoon supervisors.
My name is hymie viloria from
the muni now muni forever
campaign and also from the
tenderloin.
Thank you so much to supervisor
melgar for asking the question
to the mayor.
And it's disappointing to hear
the answer is something that is
frankly not inspiring nor did
it evoke a brand new day for
san francisco go for something
as the backbone and the
lifeblood of the city.
We sure do treat it like a
hernia.
I'm asking this board and the
mayor to help the mta solve the
problem and not rely on service
cuts for a department that has
73% approval rating the highest
in 23 years.
We understand it's a huge
deficit we face.
That is why we've been working
to address this for a couple of
years now.
And you all except for one and
including the mayor supported
prop l to fund the bus and
raise money.
Thank you for the support but
it didn't win enough to beat
the the poison pill.
Now I ask that we do something
now.
We cannot let our transit
system fail.
We need you all and the mayor
to do something or we'll end up
the way we are dealing with the
housing and the drug crisis.
Now we're both have become a
deeper problem and continue to
cost us more.
A brand new day for san
francisco requires a proactive
approach to find muni.
We can start by helping now to
stop service cuts this summer
and we can spend more time to
help fund muni in the future to
have it forever.
Thank you.
>> thank you for your comments.
Welcome to our next speaker.
>> hello.
My name is liam mckeever.
>> I live in d six.
Last week a few disabled
homeless people living in
decrepit rv using bayview
begged you to help them because
police would be evicting them
in three days on valentine's
day.
>> that's the police leaving
you.
>> what have you done for them?
I hope someone is doing
something.
Residents at the site have also
complained about the failures
to accommodate people with
disabilities, prompting
investigation by hud.
>> $15.5 million have been
wasted on this experiment and
offensive waste of our money
would have been better just to
give people the money directly.
>> but this is the soulless
circus that is played here at
city hall.
>> just before this I was at a
meeting with homeless families
from the hamilton family
shelter and MR. Murray of the
chief of health, homelessness
and family services showed up
instead of the mayor.
>> he said he was there to
listen only and why is that?
what were these people these
campaign people doing
researching during their entire
campaign?
>> so now already have informed
plans ready to deploy just
sounded like now they're
starting to gather information
and hear stories and.
He also said he couldn't
imagine what these families are
going through.
Everything.
Maybe the people who can't
imagine who have been homeless
or who are currently homeless
who understand the daily
emergency of what being
homeless is should be the ones
to be given this power since
they seem to be the only people
who will act with the urgency
this requires.
>> don't admire their
resilience create a society
where they don't need to be
resilient.
One person said every day is
like a year.
>> something needs to be done
to date.
>> they're basically just
asking to have a real shelter
to stable housing solutions.
They don't have to exit onto
the streets with their kids who
are depressed, some of which
are contemplating suicide
because of their dire straits.
That's serious enough for you?
Is that urgent enough for you?
Is that an emergency enough for
you?
I'm just like this is pathetic.
Thank you leo mckeever for your
comments.
>> welcome to our next speaker
.
>> hello.
My name is taylor and I'm the
youth t v prevention
coordinator with back revolt
against domestic violence.
I want to thank you for our
next item on the agenda which
is recognizing teen dating
violence awareness and
prevention month for the second
year with appreciation a d-10
supervisor shemar walton for
his support in bringing this to
the youth commission in its
inaugural year.
Teen dating violence is a type
of domestic violence that
affects middle high school and
young college students.
According to the cdc, 1 in 12
dating high school students
will experience sexual violence
and 1 in 12 will experience
physical violence at the hands
of a dating or a consensual
partner.
In the last 12 months right
some will experience both for a
total of up to 1 in 3 high
school students by their
graduation.
I am thankful for our
partnership with the san
francisco youth commission
asian women's shelter which is
a fellow san francisco domestic
violence consortium member and
sfi usd students for raising
this issue that affects their
fellow students.
Limiting their personal lives,
relationships, safety and
academic opportunities on and
off campus.
>> we look forward to
continuing to promote healthy
relationships skills in
accordance with the california
healthy uk act.
While also raising awareness
for the need for intervention,
resources and services for
youth 12 to 24 who are both
experiencing and perpetrating
dating violence.
Leo to bring this to you the
board of supervisors in JANUARY
of next year to amplify our
efforts for the prevention
event.
Thank you to those of you who
joined us today for wear orange
day and in co-sponsor the
resolution to support survivors
and imagine a world without
teen dating violence.
>> thank you for your comments.
>> welcome to our speaker.
Good afternoon.
My name is and I'm live sharma
speaking with developers texas
millennials.
The reason why I brought this
piece of ten it costs me
$250,000.
It's an affiliate fighting
vector with swiss watch.
If I bought that good souls
that I can sell for $2,000 what
those do for 250.
But this is worthless.
This is handcuff because city
want us to rely on disabled
wheelchair to ramp taxi
people's business.
They do not want us to give any
white collar people's business
.
>> how can we provide services
to them if we don't make any
money?
I'm there fraud don't fund any
money to empty.
>> before you bail us out taxi
drivers are in limbo.
We express our angst to
hundreds of time.
No one cares of us.
Empty your territories.
Join their hands with right
should increase their own
income to own their pet tech.
we get a bleeding to death.
>> you give us curse nor empty
for taxi drivers.
>> empty place out of the
woods.
They allowed our empty you to
pick up at the airport because
there is no ramp taxi yet
people's business in this city
.
>> so this type of business
suffocates of a life drive your
taxi cab is a misery.
Our life is terrible.
We want you to lower the price
on morality $125,000 because
empty a sold 200 medallion 11
years ago for $125,000 price.
But it kind of you know
despicable this ammunition with
us we are paying higher
interest extra amount which is
like a $125,000 extra compared
to 11 years some driver got for
that same mode only for
$125,000.
>> thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker are there any
other members of the public who
would like to address the
board?
Come on up out of there.
You go.
>> welcome.
Good afternoon sam again and
again.
You know it's as everybody
knows taxi business is
dead only we are running on the
street but there's nothing is
going on.
We're word how to feed our
families.
We're worried how to pay our
bills and we are stressed all
the time.
We don't have future.
We don't have a dream to come
to america.
even our families I mean like
our kids nobody has that dream
is killed and is killed by you
city and is killed by mta
because everyone they know well
know that we're business is
done.
There's no business and any
other state has done something
for the cab drivers release
them but why are we have been
punished have we done something
wrong for the city?
No.
We served that city for years
and we deserve something better
not to get into that slavery by
slavery and paying the bills
and all these things.
I swear to GOD we're we're
tired.
We're sick and we want you to
listen to us because it's been
years and even you ask the kids
out on the street nobody knows
even taxi anymore.
Only some very sick people
maybe 1 or 2 cars in a day or
you sit for six hours at the
airport and get somebody from
there and just to trip is not
going to be good enough to pay
your bills and feed your kids.
So we really want you guys get
together please before
something happened to us save
our lives so our families so
our kids and let us be free.
>> we are stuck.
We're okay.
I mean like and we feel like
we're in a cage all the time.
I appreciate it.
>> thank you.
Please concerned about us.
Thank you, sir, for your
comments.
>> MR. Duffy MR. PRESIDENT,
MADAM Secretary, my name is
alan duffy although I'm known
as james duffy, a curry senior
center and in the vicinity of
willow alley I'm known as
willow where a kindly spinster
took me in many years ago.
You're lucky or otherwise a
serving at a time of probably
the biggest change up in the
board since district elections
.
You're there.
You're following in the
footsteps of the great ammiano
.
I don't know too much.
I know a few things.
I do know one thing the person
who sits in the seat closest to
where public comment is I have
complete respect for that
person and in fact I once many
years ago pointed out that alan
cranston, former presidential
candidate once said in that
seat no, not actually.
Thank you, MR. Duffy for your
comments.
>> hello.
Board of supervisors and MADAM
Clerk I'm a wonder a school
garcia the director of the san
francisco youth commission my
apologies are commissioners
cannot be here today due to
school restraints.
We're here today to thank you
all for supporting teen dating
violence awareness and
prevention month.
A special shout out to the
author district nine supervisor
jackie fielder and her
legislative aide jen ferrigno
for supporting the legislation
through working out this
legislation this year.
One of the things that we've
noticed and we'll hope to
continue working with the board
on is that there's a lot of
issues regarding violence
amongst youth.
>> there's been cuts to legal
aid for youth facing domestic
violence.
The department of education has
vowed to gut title nine which
affects our youth here greatly.
We've already been seeing title
nine shortfalls and so the
commission will continue to
work with our partners our
asian woman shelter and black
women revolt to advise the
board of supervisors and the
mayor on this issue.
So thank you again for
supporting teen violence
awareness month and we hope to
continue working with you all
on this issue.
>> thank you.
Thank you, director, for your
comments.
>> welcome.
>> last if it were well about
only a flushing and the transit
you'd be fine.
>> okay.
No gov tv you make sure you are
in sync with me unlike two
weeks ago when I launched the
revolution that you can't stop
by.
It's not possible which is
about reconnecting humanity
with our fellow creatures.
All living spaces.
Yeah.
Okay.
The business as it is today is
avail no markup.
>> we have enough time now it's
raining revelations so good
story for you today there is no
time doesn't exist.
It's just a construct of human
activities.
>> so some between 5010
thousand orbits of the earth
around the sun ago a tribe
somewhere around what's called
to the eurasia fell in one of
the many traps that eternity
sets on to challenge itself on
these creations.
>> this trap was in the shape
of a mushroom that they ate and
hope it was one of these
mushrooms which are allicin you
see.
So all of a sudden the thoughts
whoa we have a vision.
We must be selected.
I don't know no matter what to
time it became a sort of a gold
up to the point where it ended
up being where on the eyes it
the jolt of the mushroom all
based on a total alice ition
you are in the tribe we are all
in a tribe.
>> we need to get out of it
because the trapper won't save
you it's easier to kill you if
you do not understand that you
are less intelligent than the
rabbit that we cut into a trap
.
Don't expect to be saved but
bite me no.
Thank you for your comments.
Are there any other members of
the public who would like to
provide general public comment?
>> MR. PRESIDENT?
All right.
>> seeing no other speakers
public comment is now closed.
MADAM Clerk let's go to our for
adoption without committee
reference.
>> agenda item number 30 item
30 was introduced for adoption
but without reference to
committee therefore unanimous
vote is required on adoption of
a resolution on first reading
today.
Alternatively a member may
require resolution on first
reading to go to committee.
>> all right.
>> seeing no one on the roster
MADAM Clerk, can you please
call the roll on item 30?
Supervisor fielder fielder eyes
supervisor mahmoud mahmoud I
supervisor randleman hi
randleman I supervisor melgar I
melgar I supervisor sutter
sutter I supervisor cheryl
cheryl I supervisor walton
walton I supervisor chan chin I
supervisor chin chin I
supervisor dorsey dorsey I and
supervisor and cardio and
guardian I there are 11 eyes
right without objection the
resolution is adopted MADAM
Clerk do we have any imperative
agenda item to report MR.
PRESIDENT then can you please
read the in memoriam?
>> today's meeting will be
adjourned in memory of the
following beloved individuals
on behalf of supervisor mandel
men MR. PRESIDENT for the late
reverend robert crummey on
behalf of supervisor melgar for
the late charles kay pesky
marian and robert j.
Bob geary on behalf of
supervisor dorsey and melgar
and in guardian on behalf of
the entire board of supervisors
as declared by the board
PRESIDENT For the late civil
service commissioner fox
crowley thank you, MADAM Clerk.
That brings us to the end of
our agenda.
>> is there any further further
business before us today that
concludes our business for
today then thank you.
>> and as there is no further
business we are adjourned